here are the stories were covering this
evo priče koje su ovo pokrivale
week in the category 5 TV newsroom a
sedmice u kategoriji 5 TV redakcija a
ransomware strike took down 23
štrajk ransomwarea 23
government agencies in Texas
vladine agencije u Teksasu
Walmart is suing Tesla's energy division
Walmart tuži Teslinu energetsku diviziju
after solar panels on seven of its doors
nakon solarnih panela na sedam njegovih vrata
caught fire
zapalilo se
researchers have found 85 Google Play
istraživači su pronašli 85 Google Play
apps with more than 8 million combined
aplikacije s više od 8 milijuna kombinovanih
downloads that forced users to view full
preuzimanja koji su prisilili korisnike da gledaju u potpunosti
screen ads Mario Kart tour was supposed
ekranski oglasi Mario Kart tour
to be available in March 2019 until
biti dostupan u martu 2019. godine do
Nintendo delayed its release to give it
Nintendo je odgodio izdanje kako bi ga prikazao
a bit more polish now the gaming giant
malo više poljski sada igrački div
is finally ready to roll out and has
je napokon spreman da se provede i ima
announced an official launch date these
objavio je službeni datum lansiranja ovih
stories are coming right up
priče stižu odmah
don't go anywhere this is the category 5
ne idite nigdje ovo je kategorija 5
dot TV newsroom covering the week's top
dot TV redakcija koja pokriva vrh sedmice
tech stories of escape Linux bias I'm
tehničke priče o bijegu zbog pristranosti Linuxa
Sacha Rickman and here are the top
Sacha Rickman i evo nas na vrhu
stories for following this week a
priče za praćenje ove nedelje a
ransomware strike took down 23
štrajk ransomwarea 23
government agencies in Texas early on
vladine agencije u Teksasu rano
August 16th a total of 23 local
16. avgusta ukupno 23 lokalna
government organizations in Texas were
vladine organizacije u Teksasu bile su
hit by a coordinated ransomware attack
pogođen koordiniranim napadom ransomwarea
the type of ransomware has not been
vrsta ransomwarea nije postojala
revealed and Texas officials asserted
otkrili i teksaški zvaničnici tvrdili
that no state networks were compromised
da nijedna državna mreža nije ugrožena
in the attack a spokesman for the
u napadu portparol za
department texas department of
odjel texas odjel
information resources or t dir said
informativnih izvora ili t dir rekao
authorities are not ready to reveal the
vlasti nisu spremne da to otkriju
names of the entities affected nor other
imena entiteta na koje utječu, niti drugih
details of the attack state and federal
detalji napada i savezne države
agencies are in the midst of a response
agencije su usred reakcije
and t v-- ir did not have information on
i t v-- ir nisu imali informacije o
when whether any of the affected
kada bilo ko od pogođenih
governmental organizations had chosen to
vladine organizacije su to odlučile
pay the ransom
plati otkupninu
but the TV ir did reveal that the
ali TV je otkrio da je
ransomware came from a single source
ransomware softver dolazi iz jednog izvora
saying quote at this time the evidence
izgovarajući u ovom trenutku dokaze
gathered indicates the attacks came from
okupljeni ukazuje da su napadi došli
one single threat actor investigations
jedna istraga aktera jedne prijetnje
into the or origin of this attack are
u ili u izvor ovog napada
ongoing
u toku
however response and recovery are at the
međutim, odgovor i oporavak su na
prior are the priority at this time and
u ovom trenutku su prioritet i
quote response teams from the t dir the
citirajte ekipe odziva iz t dir
Texas division of Emergency Management
Teksaški odjel za upravljanje u hitnim situacijama
Texas military Department Department of
Teksaški vojni odjel
Public Safety and the Texas A&amp;M
Javna sigurnost i Texas A&amp;M
University System security operations
Operacije sigurnosti univerzitetskog sistema
center and critical
središnja i kritična
in response team have all been involved
kao odgovorni tim svi su bili uključeni
in the effort to bring systems back
u nastojanju da se vrate sistemi
online as federal officials from the
online kao savezni zvaničnici iz
Department of Homeland Security the FBI
Odjeljenje za domovinsku sigurnost FBI
FEMA and other agencies it's been a bad
FEMA i druge agencije je bilo loše
year for American cities facing
godine za američke gradove koji su suočeni
ransomware attack Baltimore is still in
napada za ransomware Baltimore je i dalje u
the process of recovering just sending
proces oporavka samo slanja
out its first water bill since May and
svoj prvi račun za vodu od maja i
facing 18 million dollars in direct cost
suočeni sa 18 miliona dolara direktnog troška
and lost revenue
i izgubili prihod
elsewhere to Florida city's paid out a
negdje drugdje gradu Florida je plaćeno a
total amounting to about 1 million
ukupne vrijednosti oko 1 milion
dollars worth of cryptocurrency to
dolara u vrijednosti kripto valute
regain their data
povratiti njihove podatke
the Texas attacks are the largest
napadi u Teksasu su najveći
coordinated ransomware attack seen
viđen koordinirani napad ransomwarea
against multiple local governments but
protiv više lokalnih uprava, ali
they're not necessarily the first
nisu nužno prvi
coordinated attacks three school
koordinirani napadi tri škole
districts in northern Louisiana were hit
pogođeni su okruzi u sjevernoj Louisiani
by ransomware in a single incident in
od strane ransomwarea u jednom incidentu u
July it's not clear if the district's
Jula nije jasno da li je okrug
shared any network infrastructure my
dijelio bilo koju mrežnu infrastrukturu moja
goodness
dobrota
wasn't there like this I don't know if
nije bilo takvog ne znam da li
it's just the movies that I watch but
to su samo filmovi koje gledam ali
isn't it like we do not bow to terrorism
nije kao da se ne klanjamo terorizmu
like is that not but but it's like they
kao da to nije, ali to je kao oni
just paid a million dollars to random
samo nasumično platio milion dolara
hackers and the thing is you can call it
hakeri i stvar je u tome da je možete zvati
targeted maybe it is but realistically
ciljano možda jeste, ali realno
ransomware ten times out of nine is not
ransomware deset puta od devet nije
targeted it's just they find exploits
ciljano samo pronalaze podvige
and then they exploit it so how how is
a onda to iskorištavaju pa kako je to
it targeted in a government institution
ciljala je na vladinu instituciju
usually how it works is that the actual
obično kako funkcionira je ono što je stvarno
human well know it starts with a script
ljudi dobro znaju da počinje sa scenarijem
the scripts look for exploits on the web
skripte traže podvige na webu
so these are unpatched windows systems
pa su ovo neispavani prozori
routers that have default passwords
usmjerivači koji imaju zadane lozinke
things like that once it finds one it
takve stvari jednom kada ga pronađu
then tries to compromise and it will
onda pokušava napraviti kompromis i hoće
notify the person who's attacking the
obavesti osobu koja napada
the individual hey I found one here's
pojedine hej našao sam jednog ovdje
the credentials you can log in they'll
vjerodajnice u koje se možete prijaviti oni će se prijaviti
log in and then they'll figure out hey
prijavite se i tada će shvatiti hej
they have two hundred computers or they
imaju dvjesto računara ili oni
have ten thousand computers oh look at
ima deset hiljada računara
this I'm in I'm into the school board so
ovo sam u, tako sam u školskom odboru
what do they do they then sell that
šta rade oni to prodaju
information
informacija
that login information well sometimes
te informacije za prijavu ponekad
they'll install a couple things first to
prvo će instalirati nekoliko stvari
make sure that they have guaranteed
pobrinite se da garantiraju
their access just so that you don't you
njihov pristup samo tako da vi ne
don't make it too easy for them to patch
nemojte ih previše lako zakrpati
it and then they sell it on the dark web
to i onda prodaju na tamnom webu
like let's sell that information so is
kao da prodajemo te informacije
it targeted well kind of but it started
ciljala je dobro, ali počela je
with you have unpatched systems and then
sa sobom imate neupadljive sisteme i tada
it became targeted when they realized
postala je meta kad su shvatili
what they had found what they had been
što su našli ono što su bili
able to compromise and then sell it to
u mogućnosti da naprave kompromis i onda ga prodaju
the next highest bidder and then that
sledeći najveći ponuđač i onda to
bitter is the one who says ok I'm gonna
ogorčen je onaj koji kaže ok
try to make a million dollars I'm gonna
pokušaj zaraditi milion dolara koje ću
encrypt all these files over the weekend
šifrirajte sve ove datoteke preko vikenda
right yeah unfortunately it seems to be
Da, nažalost, izgleda
like the new norm we kind of started to
poput nove norme koju smo nekako započeli
fall into complacency there for about
upadati u samozadovoljstvo tamo oko
six months leading up to about three
šest mjeseci do približno tri
weeks ago I mean unless you're in the
Prije nekoliko tjedana mislim ako niste u
States you know working for the
Države za koje znate da rade za
government that it's really it had
vlada da je to zaista i bila
tapered off for a while it was really
stvarno se suzdržao neko vrijeme, zaista je
bad 2017 2018 2019 has not seen as much
loša 2017. 2018. 2019. nije vidjela toliko
it's like it seems like it has tapered
kao da se čini kao da se suzio
off maybe people have gotten wise and
možda su ljudi postali mudri i
patched their systems and so maybe that
krpao njihove sisteme i tako možda to
but now more exploits come out we've
ali sada dolazi do većeg broja iskorištavanja
talked about hey patch your systems
razgovarali o hej patchu vaših sistema
because Microsoft has already revealed
jer je Microsoft već otkrio
that there are newly found exploits that
da postoje novootkriveni podvizi koji
are in the wild that can be compromised
nalaze se u divljini koja može biti ugrožena
so hey if they didn't patch their
pa hej ako ih nisu zakrpili
systems call it targeted if you want
Sistemi ga nazivaju ciljanim ako želite
it's not targeted they're just not
nije ciljano jednostavno nisu
patched right so but that said okay so
zakrpano točno, ali to je reklo da treba
we fell into complacency thinking hey
pali smo u samozadovoljstvo misleći hej
the things have tapered off no now it's
stvari su se smanjile, ne sada
back on the rise again we're seeing
ponovo u usponu koji vidimo
multiple ransomware attacks even in
više napada ransomwarea čak i u
small communities every single week and
male zajednice svake nedelje i
and that's a really dangerous thing and
a to je stvarno opasna stvar i
the truth of the matter is when you're
istina je u tome kad jesi
desperate you're gonna end up paying the
očajnički ćete završiti plaćanje
ransom like you're desperate I hope not
otkup kao da si očajan, nadam se da ne
I hope not too but at the same time if I
Nadam se ne previše, ali istovremeno, ako i ja
if all of my business was based on the
ako bi se sve moje poslovanje temeljilo na
fact that I needed I know access what
činjenica da mi je potreban znam pristup čemu
other choice nation yeah and there's
Da, tu je i drugi izbor
another side to this where you're naming
druga strana ovome gde vi dajete imena
off all these agencies that are working
od svih ovih agencija koje rade
with them to recover and I just went
s njima da se oporavim i upravo sam otišao
through ransomware attack and it's like
putem napada ransomwarea i to je slično
where are these agencies to help me I
gdje su ove agencije koje mi pomažu
didn't personally one of my customers
nisam lično jedan od mojih kupaca
did
jeste
and it was up to me to to remedy it for
a na meni je bilo da to popravim
them well they didn't pay the ransom
oni dobro nisu platili otkupninu
they paid my hourly wage and that was
oni su mi isplaćivali satnicu i to je bilo
less than the rant it was less than the
manje od onog što je bilo manje nego što je bilo
ransom but but still a hefty fine
otkupnine, ali još uvijek teška kazna
right but but the fact is is that you
ali činjenica je da si ti
know that was my my burden my stress to
znajte da je to moj teret
deal with it throughout the process
baviti se tim tokom celog procesa
because backups were not what they
jer sigurnosne kopije nisu bile to
should have been and and so on so but
trebalo je biti i tako dalje, ali
they've got these massive industries
oni imaju ove masovne industrije
that will come in and and help them
koji će doći i pomoći im
recover but we can't get backwards and
oporavimo se, ali ne možemo nazad i
and you can't pay these folks I know
i ne možete platiti ove ljude koje znam
that's a really hard thing
to je stvarno teška stvar
look look for volume shadow copies if
potražite kopije sjena volumena ako
you ever get hit another thing that's
ikad budete pogođeni drugom stvari koja je to
really interesting not to take too much
stvarno zanimljivo ne uzimati previše
time I know you want to move on but if I
vreme znam da želite da nastavite dalje, ali ako ja
can give you one tip this is a really
mogu vam dati jedan savjet ovo je stvarno
interesting fact and as soon as I say it
zanimljiva činjenica i čim to izgovorim
I think I think that the malicious
Mislim da mislim da su zlonamjerni
parties that are watching are gonna be
stranke koje gledaju biće
oh we need to fix that volume shadow
oh, moramo da popravimo onu volumen sjene
copies are like copies of your files
kopije su kao kopije vaših datoteka
that you can revert to the previous
koji možete vratiti na prethodni
version on Windows okay very very handy
verzija za Windows u redu, vrlo zgodna
if you have them and you need to revert
ako ih imate i trebate ponovo uzvratiti
go back in time so if you have all your
Vratite se u vrijeme pa ako imate sve svoje
shadow copies and you get hacked or hit
kopije u sjeni i vi ćete biti hakirani ili pogođeni
by ransomware sometimes well if you have
by ransomware ponekad dobro ako i imate
a volume Shadow Copy you can go back to
Kopija sjena volumena na koju se možete vratiti
the previous version of the file and you
prethodnoj verziji datoteke i vi
can do it on a whole drive so you can
možete to raditi na cijelom pogonu, tako da možete
just undo the damage just like that but
samo poništite štetu samo tako, ali
these days the malicious parties are
ovih su dana zlonamerne zabave
getting smart and they're removing the
postaju pametni i uklanjaju
volume shadow copies from the computer
kopije sjena volumena s računala
this particular instance the hacker
ovaj konkretni slučaj hakera
whoever coded it will only remove volume
ko ga je kodirao, ukloniće samo volumen
shadow copies from C from the C Drive so
sjene kopije sa C s C pogona tako
the interesting fact about that is if
zanimljiva činjenica o tome je ako
your system drive or your data drive is
vaš sistemski pogon ili vaš pogon podataka
not C C colon in Wales like if it was D
a ne CC debelo crijevo u Velsu kao da je to D
or Z or P or whatever it still have it
ili Z ili P ili šta god ga još ima
it it may have you may have still had
možda ste je imali
the volume shadow copies the data would
sjena volumena kopira podatke koje bi
have still been encrypted but they
još uvek su šifrirani ali oni
didn't think to delete the volume shadow
nije mislio izbrisati sjenu glasnoće
copies from any Drive other than C right
kopije s bilo kojeg Diska osim C prava
now that's only the case of the
sada je to samo slučaj
particular malware that I was dealing
određeni zlonamjerni softver kojim sam se bavio
with that was a really stupid bonehead
s tim je bio stvarno glup kosti glave
mistake on the on the part of the hacker
greška sa strane hakera
but it gave me an opportunity
ali pružila mi je priliku
to restore some of the networking
za obnovu nekih umrežavanja
because there were volume shadow copies
jer su postojale kopije u sjeni
of the mounted volumes right right so it
montirane količine pravo tako da je tako
was a whole different scenario so so
bio je sasvim drugačiji scenarij pa je tako
watch out for that blowing shadow copies
pripazite na kopije sjene
could be your friend that's for sure
mogao biti vaš prijatelj to je sigurno
Walmart is suing Tesla's energy division
Walmart tuži Teslinu energetsku diviziju
after solar panels on seven of its
nakon solarnih panela na sedam njih
stores caught fire
prodavnice zapaljene
Walmart's legal team alleged that the
Walmartov pravni tim tvrdio je da
firm was negligent and how it installed
firma je bila nemarna i kako je instalirala
the panels on the roofs of the stores
ploče na krovovima prodavnica
court documents describe a string of
sudski dokumenti opisuju niz od
fires that occurred between 2012 and
požari koji su se dogodili između 2012. i
2018 at Walmart locations in Ohio
2018. godine na Walmart lokacijama u Ohiju
Marylyn and California the first fire
Marylyn i California prvi požar
occurred at a Walmart store in Long
dogodila se u prodavaonici Walmart u Longu
Beach California in 2012 another in
Plaža Kalifornija 2012. još jedan u
Beavercreek Ohio in March 2018 so our
Beavercreek Ohio u martu 2018. godine tako naš
customers evacuated and the store closed
kupci su se evakuisali, a prodavnica zatvorena
for eight days oh this court documents a
za osam dana oh ovaj sudski dokument a
quote to state the obvious a properly
citiram da se ispravno navede očigledno
designed installed inspected and
dizajniran instaliran pregledan i
maintained solar systems do not
održavani solarni sistemi nemaju
spontaneously combust end quote
spontano gorljivi krajnji citat
Walmart is asking Tesla to remove solar
Walmart traži od Tesle da ukloni solarnu energiju
panels from all of its stores and to pay
ploče iz svih svojih trgovina i za plaćanje
damages
oštećenja
Tesla's share price fell on news of the
Teslina cijena dionica pala je na vijestima o tome
Walmart lawsuit which was filed in the
Tužba Walmart koja je podnesena u
New York State Supreme Court last
Poslednji Vrhovni sud države Njujork
Tuesday that is such a crying shame it
Utorak koji je takav plač sramota je
puts a real negative spin on solar
pravi pravi negativni spin na solarni
panels doesn't have to be now I'm
paneli ne moraju biti sad ja
thinking of putting solar panels on the
razmišljam o stavljanju solarnih panela na
roof of the house and it's like I don't
krov kuće i kao da ne radim
want my house to catch fire i I don't
želim da se moja kuća zapali, a ja ne
think solar panels are that dangerous I
mislim da su solarni paneli toliko opasni ja
mean I realize that maybe since I had
znači shvaćam da možda otkad jesam
seven stores with solar panels catch
sedam trgovina sa solarnim pločama privlači
fire and I realized that that's a
vatra i shvatio sam da je to a
tragedy and be closed for eight days is
tragedija i biti zatvoren osam dana je
bad and I don't want to diminish the
loše i ne želim umanjivati ​​to
fact that I'm sure that there was damage
činjenica da sam siguran da je došlo do štete
I think that the pros outweigh the cons
Mislim da profesionalci nadmašuju nedostatke
as far as solar panels go these things
što se tiče ovih solarnih panela
can like this I think how long I want to
mogu ovako da mislim koliko dugo to želim
know how long were they installed for
znam koliko dugo su ih instalirali
right that's I guess the question that
tačno, pretpostavljam da je pitanje u tome
the burning questions it because in the
goruće ga pita jer u
statement from Walmart they said
izjavu iz Walmarta rekli su
properly maintained well were you
pravilno održavana dobro ste bili
properly maintaining it i I know
pravilno održavajući to znam
customers who say they've been properly
kupci koji kažu da su pravilno postupili
maintaining their server and they're
održavajući svoj poslužitelj i oni su
using an e o al version of server
koristeći eo al verziju poslužitelja
like could could lightning have hit it
kao da bi ga mogla udariti munja
could clear that have been the case I
mogao sam jasno da je to slučaj i ja
don't know you think they'd have a
ne znam da misliš da bi imali
lightning tower or some tree nearby
gromobrana ili nekog drveta u blizini
that's a bit taller than the building I
to je malo više od zgrade koju imam
would like to know how many stores Tesla
Volio bih znati koliko dućana Tesla
has solar panels on because yours
ima solarne panele jer je vaš
doesn't seem like a huge number it feels
ne izgleda kao ogroman broj koji se oseća
yeah was it just a trial like where
da, bilo je to samo suđenje poput toga
there were eight stores and seven of
bilo je osam prodavnica i sedam
them caught on fire or was it
uhvatili ih na vatri ili je bilo
millions of stores yeah see my neighbor
milion dućana da vidim mog susjeda
two doors down has solar panels all over
dva vrata dolje imaju solarne panele po cijelom
their entire roof they're at time yeah
cijeli njihov krov oni su na vrijeme
like it's gonna burn I'm not scared
kao da će izgorjeti nisam uplašena
they're not scared I feel like I feel
nisu uplašeni, osjećam se kao da se osjećam
like this story is weird too maybe yes
kao da je i ova priča čudna možda je i da
this is what I'm feeling like it is this
to je ono zbog čega se osjećam
our advantage at category 5 TV that we
naša prednost u kategoriji kategorije 5 koju smo
can have this conversation in the news
može li ovaj razgovor u vestima
and say is is media hyping this is media
i recite da je medijski hyping ovo je media
making it sound like this is a bigger
što zvuči kao da je ovo veće
deal than it is and it's affecting
dogovor nego što je i to utiče
stocks of Tesla who are like making a
zalihe Tesle koje kao da prave
world of difference
svijet razlike
yeah Tesla is trying really really hard
da Tesla se jako trudi
really hard well I'm not gonna even go
jako teško, neću ni ići
there but I just I feel like stop
tamo, ali jednostavno se osjećam kao da stanem
picking on Tesla and and this is the
branje Tesle i to je ono
fact they're not giving all the facts
zapravo, oni ne navode sve činjenice
they're not giving you all the details
ne daju vam sve detalje
they're not saying ok there were there
ne kažu da je bilo ondje
were actually two thousand stores there
zapravo je bilo dvije hiljade prodavnica
were actually you know these ones they
da li ste stvarno znali ove
they decided to have a local company
oni su odlučili da imaju lokalno preduzeće
install them instead of test I don't
instalirajte ih umjesto testa ne
know these things
znam ove stvari
were the official installers you know it
bili su službeni instalateri kojih vi znate
could be anything maybe it was a flat
moglo biti bilo što, možda je stan
roof and it flooded a bit and it shorted
krova i malo je poplavio i on se skratio
something out was it sabotage right all
nešto napolju bila je to sabotaža u redu
these things so don't let's not lose
te stvari, zato nemojmo zaboraviti
hope in the technology and the the fact
nada u tehnologiju i činjenicu
that this can make a whole world of good
da se time može stvoriti čitav svijet dobra
for for like emissions hey we can tap
jer za emisije možemo iskoristiti hej
into the Sun I make sense juice about
na Sunce za koji imam smisla
green power like your wind Sun anything
zelena snaga poput vašeg vjetra Sunce ništa
you can do to make it so that you're not
možete to učiniti tako da niste
just digging up fossil fuels and burning
samo kopanje fosilnih goriva i spaljivanje
them yeah we we spoke with anusha ask
oni da, razgovarali smo sa anusha askom
you and
ti i
about her technology at her company ship
o njenoj tehnologiji na brodu njene kompanije
and Shore environmental and in that
i Shore ekološka i u tome
discussion she mentioned how they can
diskusije ona je spomenula kako mogu
convert emissions into the heat for the
pretvoriti emisije u toplinu za
building and water heating and things
zgrada i grijanje vode i stvari
like that how cool is that and now okay
kao da je to super i sad je u redu
so solar panels yeah we can power things
pa solarni paneli da, možemo da napajamo stvari
we can generate heat we can we can heat
možemo stvarati toplinu, možemo je grijati
the pool we can heat the water of that
bazen možemo da grejemo vodu iz toga
you're using to wash your hands and have
koju koristiš za pranje ruku i jesti
a shower right like these are all things
tuš kao što su to sve su stvari
that can be done through just the Sun
to se može postići kroz samo Sunce
don't lose hope don't ya don't let media
ne gubite nadu da ne puštate medije
hype it don't listen to this story
ne slušaj ovu priču
listen to the conversation after where
slušajte razgovor nakon čega
we put it straight exactly yes and
direktno kažemo da i
comment below and tell us how right we
komentar ispod i recite nam koliko smo u pravu
are how right we are I would really
koliko smo u pravu, zaista bih
appreciate that just once in a while
cijenite to samo jednom s vremena na vrijeme
YouTube just tell us how 85 Google Play
YouTube nam samo govori kako 85 Google Play
apps with more than 8 million combined
aplikacije s više od 8 milijuna kombinovanih
downloads that force users to view full
preuzimanja koji prisiljavaju korisnike da gledaju u potpunosti
screen ads the apps which poses
na ekranu prikazuje aplikacije koje predstavljaju
photography and gaming programs
programi za fotografije i igre
contained a family of adware that was
sadržavala je porodicu adwarea koja je
highly disruptive to end-users
vrlo razarajući za krajnje korisnike
once installed the apps displayed ads in
nakon instaliranja aplikacija prikazanih oglasa u
full screen a setting that forced users
postavka preko cijelog ekrana koja prisiljava korisnike
to view the entire duration of an ad
da biste pregledali cjelokupno trajanje oglasa
before being able to close the window or
pre nego što ste mogli zatvoriti prozor ili
to get back into the app the apps showed
da se vratite u aplikaciju koju su aplikacije pokazale
an ad every 5 minutes oh the people
oglas svakih 5 minuta oh ljudi
operating the platform had the ability
upravljanje platformom je imalo sposobnost
to remotely change the frequency the
za daljinsko mijenjanje frekvencije
adware used several tricks to evade
adware je koristio nekoliko trikova kako bi izbjegao
detection and removal a half an hour
otkrivanje i uklanjanje pola sata
after being installed for instance an
nakon instaliranja, na primjer
app would hide its icon and create a
aplikacija bi sakrila svoju ikonu i stvorila
shortcut on the device home screen
prečac na početnom ekranu uređaja
hiding the icon prevented the apps from
sakrivanje ikone sprečilo je aplikacije u
being uninstalled by dragging and
deinstalirati povlačenjem i
dropping the icon to the uninstall
ispuštanje ikone za deinstaliranje
section of the device screen Android 8
odjeljak na ekranu uređaja Android 8
and later versions require user
i novije verzije zahtijevaju korisnika
confirmation before an app can create a
potvrdu prije nego što aplikacija može stvoriti
shortcut but even if users of these
prečica, ali čak i ako ih korisnici koriste
versions didn't agree the icon would
verzije se nisu složile da će ikona biti
nonetheless remain hidden Trend Micro
bez obzira na to, ostaju skriveni Trend Micro
who made the discovery
ko je otkrio
privately reported the apps to Google
privatno je prijavio aplikacije Googleu
and Google then removed the apps from
a Google je tada uklonio aplikacije iz
play so
igrati tako
okay but they were removed yeah and I
ok, ali uklonjeni su da i ja
and I did hear as well that some of
a čuo sam i da su neki
these apps were objectionable so the
ove su aplikacije bile sporne pa su
problem with that is like okay my kids
problem s tim je u redu, moja djeca
use the phone all the time right they
koriste telefon cijelo vrijeme dobro
install apps you know we let them
instalirajte aplikacije za koje znate da smo im to dozvolili
install games and stuff and only the
instalirajte igre i stvari i samo
free ones right and you have a certain
besplatni su, a imate određeno
amount of trust and we do have a certain
količinu poverenja i imamo je izvesno
amount of trust in Google Play and the
povjerenje u Google Play i
App Store and and trust that hey these
App Store i imajte povjerenja u to
things have been tested for any kind of
stvari su testirane na bilo koju vrstu
malware and they do get through the
zlonamjerni softver i oni prolaze kroz
cracks sometimes because hackers are
pukotine ponekad jer hakeri jesu
clever
pametna
advertisers are clever they're getting
oglašivači su pametni
paid first isn't it it's not free that
plaćeno prvo nije li to besplatno
is tricky business hiding the icon you
je lukav posao skrivanje ikone koju vi
know how many times I've had like an
znam koliko puta sam imao takav
idiot boy here Morse I download an app
idiot dečko Morse, preuzimam aplikaciju
and a Michael what have I done
i Michael što sam učinio
uninstall how horrible how do I remove
deinstalirajte koliko grozno kako da uklonim
the LG stuff garbage that it comes with
LG puni smeće koje dolazi
how horrible would it be if then you
kako bi bilo grozno da ste to tada
couldn't remove it at all right yeah Oh
nisam mogao ukloniti u redu da. Oh
or you don't even see it so you don't
ili ga ni ne vidite pa ne
even know it's running in the background
čak znam da radi u pozadini
it just it's not even there oh that's
to jednostavno nije ni oh, to je
dirty guys don't be doing that yeah
prljavi dečki to ne rade
Mario Kart tour was supposed to be
Mario Kart trebao je biti obilazak
available in March 2019 until Nintendo
dostupno u ožujku 2019. do Nintendoa
delayed its release to give it a bit
odgodio izdanje da bi mu malo dao
more polish and now the gaming giant is
više poljski, a sada je i div gigant
finally ready to roll out and has
napokon spreman za uvrtanje i ima
announced an official launch date the
objavila je službeni datum lansiranja
Mario Kart Tour website even shows that
Web stranica Mario Kart Tour to čak pokazuje
pre registrations are now open for both
predbilježbe su sada otvorene za obje
Android and iOS users so they can be
Korisnici Android-a i iOS-a kako bi mogli biti
notified as soon as the game is ready to
obavešteni čim je igra spremna
download but the official word is Mario
preuzimanje, ali službena riječ je Mario
Kart tour will be available on your
Kart obilazak bit će dostupan na vašoj stranici
smartphone September 25th the game is
smartfon 25. septembra igra je
free to start which means players will
slobodno za početak, što znači da igrači hoće
have to decide whether to spend money on
moraju odlučiti da li će trošiti novac
microtransactions to unlock features and
mikrotransakcije za otključavanje funkcija i
perhaps even characters Nintendo has
možda čak i likove koje Nintendo ima
promised to release more details about
obećao da će objaviti više detalja o
the game as its release date approaches
igra kako se približava datum izlaska
and some people give a hard time to
a nekima je to teško
nintendo over like this freemium model
nintendo preko ovog freemium modela
right
tačno
but anyone who owns a Nintendo switch
ali svako ko je vlasnik Nintendo sklopke
like you already know that like that's
kao da to već znate
the way the Nintendo has been for some
način na koji je Nintendo bio za neke
time it's like hey yeah we'll let you
vrijeme je kao da, dopustit ćemo vam
play for free but if you want
igrajte besplatno, ali ako želite
tap into my daughter was concerned today
danas se brinula za moju kćer
because she had accidentally spawned
jer se ona slučajno rodila
about a billion sheep in her Minecraft
oko milijardu ovaca u njenom Minecraftu
world and it was crashing and she
svijetu i rušilo se i ona
couldn't get back in and everything
nisam mogao da se vratim i sve
she's like I don't have a Nintendo
ona je kao da nemam Nintendo
account so I can't back it up only you
računa pa ne mogu to stvoriti samo vi
got to pay 50 bucks for that Nintendo
moram platiti 50 dolara za taj Nintendo
account right right so it's like the the
račun pravo, tako da je kao onaj
infrastructure is already there that's
infrastruktura je već tu, to je
how they do things and it makes sense oh
kako rade stvari i ima smisla oh
you have to make money but I guess phone
morate zaraditi, ali pretpostavljam telefonom
users are not really used to that model
korisnici zapravo nisu navikli na taj model
like the PlayStation online yeah you're
poput PlayStationa na mreži, da, jesi
used to it yeah Nintendo is it called
navikao na to da, Nintendo se tako zove
Nintendo Online I think you're used to
Nintendo Online Mislim da ste navikli
it so if I were to give a child my phone
pa ako bih djetetu dao telefon
how easy is it to actually do these
koliko je lako to zapravo učiniti
microtransactions that's the thing yeah
mikrotransakcije to je stvar
okay I ever tell you how that happened
Ok, ikad vam kažem kako se to dogodilo
when I first got a Android TV set-top
kada sam prvi put nabavio Android TV set-top
box no I let you log into your Google
okvir ne. Dopuštam vam da se prijavite na svoj Google
account okay and your Google Account is
račun je u redu, a vaš Google račun je
associated with your credit card
povezan sa vašom kreditnom karticom
uh-huh right yeah yeah and I got
uh, da, da, da, i jesam
notifications I'm sitting at my desk and
Obavijesti sjedim za svojim stolom i
I kept getting in my phone was buzzing
Neprestano mi je zujalo u telefonu
in my pocket I pulled it out and it was
u džepu sam ga izvukao i bilo je
like email after email one dollar one
poput e-pošte nakon slanja e-pošte po jedan dolar
dollar one dollar one dollar wonder $500
dolar jedan dolar jedan dolar čudo 500 dolara
plus who is that
plus ko je to
and so I I called Becca my wife and I
i tako sam nazvao Beku, moju ženu i ja
said I said turn off the TV whatever and
rekao sam da sam isključio televizor i šta god
she's like but Zack my son is playing a
ona je poput, ali Zack se igra mog sina
game I said turn it off now it was just
igra Rekao sam da isključite to sad samo
racking up he apparently was sitting
držeći se, očito je sjedio
there in some race car game where you
tamo u nekoj igri trkačkih automobila gdje i ti
can like push the button over and over
može poput pritiska na dugme ponovo i ponovo
and over again to increase your your
i ponovo da povećate svoje
power of the car or something and it's
snaga automobila ili nešto slično
taken a dollar at a time to do I hope
uzimam dolar odjednom da se nadam
you won that race
pobijedili ste u toj utrci
they were great about it Amazon because
bili su sjajni u vezi s tim Amazonom jer
I think this was actually an Amazon I
Mislim da je ovo zapravo bila Amazonija I
know it was it wasn't Google it was an
znajte da nije Google, već to
Amazon fire stick oh yeah that's how it
Amazonski vatreni štap, da, tako je to
happened it was my Amazon account so I
dogodilo se da je to bio moj račun na Amazonu pa sam
contacted Amazon they reversed it it was
kontaktirali Amazon i preokrenuli to
no problem but a real learning
nije problem, nego stvarno učenje
experience so then I started adding my
iskustvo pa sam tada počeo dodavati svoje
password to every device that I shared
lozinku za svaki uređaj koji sam dijelio
with the kids
sa decom
right you've got to do it so parents
zar ne moraš to učiniti tako roditelji
yeah yeah this new game right like
da da, ova nova igra baš poput
you'll you want to watch out for that
na to želite da pazite
you'll for sure want a polka phone F
sigurno želite polka telefon F
ones I love it has it has second space
one koje volim da ima drugi prostor
so I have my own profile for everything
pa za sve imam svoj profil
and then I have a second one that has
a onda imam drugi koji ima
just the games for the kids and and I
samo igre za djecu i ja
use that profile when I do now I use it
koristim taj profil kada ga sada koristim
when I do demonstrations on the air
kada radim demonstracije u eteru
because then if my wife messages me and
jer onda ako mi supruga pošalje poruku i
it pops up like private messages it
iskoči kao privatne poruke
doesn't show up on the air which we've
ne prikazuje se u eteru koji imamo
had happen before it's all her romantic
dogodilo se prije nego što je sve bilo romantično
messages as were on the air so that's a
poruke kao da su u eteru, tako da je to
cool feature so turn on the password
cool funkcija, pa uključite lozinku
protection anyway should should protect
zaštitu ionako treba zaštititi
you I want to take a quick look at our
želite da pogledamo naše
cryptocurrency market as of 1800 hours
tržište kriptovaluta već od 1800 sati
Wednesday August 28 2019 Bitcoin is down
Srijeda, 28. avgusta 2019. Bitcoin je u padu
quite a bit four hundred five dollars
prilično četiri stotine pet dolara
down to nine thousand six hundred
sve do devet hiljada šest stotina
seventy six dollars and 28 cents
sedamdeset šest dolara i 28 centi
Facebook Libre is holding steady at zero
Facebook Libre drži se čvrsto na nuli
because it's not actually trading yet
jer to zapravo još nije trgovanje
but one day we're gonna find that it is
ali jednog dana otkrit ćemo da jeste
trading and that will be exciting
trgovanja i to će biti uzbudljivo
litecoin is also down everything's down
Litecoin je takođe sve manji
this week sixty six dollars and forty
ove sedmice šezdeset šest dolara i četrdeset
cents is the Fiat value of that in US
centi je vrijednost Fiata u SAD-u
dollars
dolara
if theoria MS down at 170 201 Manero at
ako teorija MS padne na 170 201 Manero na
72 13 turtle coin is at 0.49 ten
Kovanica od 72 kornjače iznosi 0,49 deset
thousandths of a cent and another coin
hiljadu centa i još jedan novčić
that has lost a lot we've called it
to je mnogo izgubilo kako smo to nazvali
stellite and then they changed their
stellit i onda su promijenili svoj
name to torque and then they were doing
ime momenta i onda su to radili
quite well this week they've lost
prilično su dobro ove nedelje izgubili
another zero point five six ten
još jedna nulta točka pet šest deset
thousandth of a cent so they basically
tisućinu centa, tako da u osnovi
cut the coin in half and are you ready
prerežite novčić na pola i jeste li spremni
for this they've changed their name
zbog toga su promenili ime
again I don't know what they're doing
opet ne znam šta rade
but Scala is the name of the coin the
ali Scala je ime kovanice
cryptocurrency formerly known as yeah
cryptocurrency nekad poznata kao da
exactly so you go to stellite and it
tačno tako da ideš na stellit i to
says it's now called torque and then you
kaže da se to sada zove moment i onda ti
go to torque and it's now called Scala
idite na obrtni moment i to se sada zove Scala
Scala
Scala
but torque was doing really well and
ali okretni moment je bio dobar i
then Scala is now you know I don't know
onda je Scala sada znaš ja ne znam
if people have lost confidence in it
ako su ljudi izgubili povjerenje u to
because and you know what it could also
jer i znate što bi to takođe moglo
be it's a pain in the butt when they
biti to bol u guzi kad one
change their coins so much right because
toliko promijenili svoje kovanice jer
if I'm mining I find crypto mining I
ako rudam, pronaći ću kriptovalute I
have to reinstall and reconfigure
moraju ponovo instalirati i konfigurirati
everything and install the new crypto
sve i instalirajte novu kriptovalutu
miner
rudar
install the new wallets and everything
instalirajte nove novčanike i svašta
that's like oh you know what I'm just
to je kao da znate šta sam upravo ja
moving on to a different coin turtle
prelazi na drugačiju kornjaču od novčića
coin has been pretty stable and and it's
kovanica je bila prilično stabilna i to je
another micro coin they should have kept
još jedan mikro-novac koji su trebali da zadrže
it at torque that's a solid main I think
mislim da je okretni moment to solidno glavno
it's just another case of they probably
to je vjerovatno još jedan slučaj
found a company that said we already on
pronašli smo tvrtku koja je rekla da već idemo
that train trade mark maybe they should
taj zaštitni znak možda bi trebao
start googling the names that they come
počnite gutati imena koja dolaze
up with I got an idea let's call it
imam ideju nazovimo je
Tesla right you know
Tesla zar ne znaš
yeah and that's your coins I can tell
da i to su vaši novčići
you I will put money on the fact that it
uložit ću novac na to
won Facebook come the Facebook Libre
osvojeni Facebook došli su Facebook Libre
yeah it'll have to gain its first week
da, morat će dobiti prvu sedmicu
you can't go yep so invest now oh wait
ne možete ići tako da uložite sada oh čekaj
you can't
ne možeš
yeah yeah big thanks Roy W Nash in our
da, da, hvala Roy W Nash u našem
community of viewers four seven eight
zajednica gledalaca četiri sedam osam
stories to us this week thanks for
priče ove nedelje hvala na
watching the category-five TV newsroom
gledajući TV redakciju kategorije pet
don't forget to Like and subscribe for
ne zaboravite da se Sviđate i pretplatite se
all your tech news with a slight Linux
sve vaše vijesti o tehnologiji sa laganim Linuxom
bias and for more free content be sure
pristranosti i za više besplatnog sadržaja budite sigurni
to check out our web site from the
da biste provjerili našu web stranicu sa
category-five TV newsroom I'm Sasha
kategorija pet TV redakcije Ja sam Saša
Rickman and I'm Ravi Ferguson
Rickman i ja Ravi Ferguson